宇宙就是這樣
The cosmos is all there is
過去是這樣
or ever was,
以後還是這樣
or ever will be
跟我來
Come with me.
30多年前
A generation ago,
天文學家卡爾·薩根站在這裏
the astronomer Carl Sagan stood here
1980年 卡爾·薩根在PBS拍攝了紀錄片《卡爾·薩根的宇宙》
其紀錄片在超過60個國家播出 影響著全世界超過五億人口
帶領全世界數億人
and launched hundreds of millions of us
進行了一場歷險
on a great adventure...
用科學去探索宇宙的奧秘
the exploration of the universe revealed by science.
是時候再次探險了
It's time to get going again.
這場即將開始的旅行會向我們展示
We're about to begin a journey that will take us
從最微小的到無窮大的
from the infinitesimal to the infinite,
從時間的開始到遙遠的未來
from the dawn of time to the distant future.
我們會探索不同的世界和星系
We'll explore galaxies and suns and worlds,
在時間和空間的組合中暢遊
surf the gravity waves of space-time,
接觸生活在火中和冰中的生物
encounter beings that live in fire and ice,
探索永恆不滅的星系
explore the planets of stars that never die,
瞭解和恆星一樣大的原子
discover atoms as massive as suns
還有比原子還小的宇宙
and universes smaller than atoms.
這也是關於人類的故事
Cosmos is also a story about us.
這也是先人們對星空研究的史詩長篇
It's the saga of how wandering bands of hunters and gatherers found their way to the stars,
眾多英雄共同譜寫的史詩
one adventure with many heroes.
我們需要想像力來完成這次歷險
To make this journey,we'll need imagination.
但僅靠想像力是不夠的
But imagination alone is not enough
因為大自然的真實樣子是超乎想像的神奇
because the reality of nature is far more wondrous than anything we can imagine.
使這次的歷險因為幾代研究人員的努力成為可能
This adventure is made possible by generations of searchers
他們嚴格地堅持一套簡單的規則
strictly adhering to a simple set of rules...
以試驗和觀察結果檢驗觀點
test ideas by experiment and observation,
以通過檢驗的觀點為基礎
build on those ideas that pass the test,
摒棄未通過檢驗的
reject the ones that fail,
用證據說話
follow the evidence wherever it leads
並對一切存疑
and question everything.
接受這些規則
Accept these terms,
這就是你的宇宙
and the cosmos is yours.
跟我來吧
Now come with me.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第一集
在這艘想像之舟中
In this ship of the Imagination,
不受空間和時間的限制
free from the shackles of space and time,
我們可以去任何地方
we can go anywhere.
如果你想知道我們身處太空何處
If you want to see where we are in space,
只要看向窗外
just look out the front window.
以時間來說 過去就在我們腳下
In the dimension of time, the past lies beneath us.
這就是地球2.5億年前的樣子
Here's what Earth looked like 250 million years ago.
抬頭 就可以看到未來的樣子
If you want to see the future, look up.
這就是2.5億年後可能的樣子
And this is how it could appear 250 million years from now.
如果我們要嘗試
If we're going to be venturing out
在極度廣闊的宇宙中聯繫
into the farthest reaches of the cosmos,
我們需要知道自己的宇宙地址
we need to know our cosmic address,
這就是我們地址的第一行
and this is the first line of that address.
地球
我們現在離開地球 這個我們僅有的家園
We're leaving the Earth, the only home we've ever known,
向更加寬廣的宇宙進發
for the farthest reaches of the cosmos.
我們最近的鄰居 月球 沒有大氣層
Our nearest neighbor, the Moon, has no sky,
沒有海洋 沒有生命
no ocean, no life...
只有天體撞擊的傷痕
just the scars of cosmic impacts.
我們的地球為我們提供了風和浪
Our star powers the wind and the waves
為地球表面一切的生物提供能量
and all the life on the surface of our world.
從水星開始
The Sun holds all the worlds of the solar system
整個太陽系都被太陽的引力場所包圍
in its gravitational embrace, starting with Mercury...
直到雲層覆蓋的金星
...to cloud-covered Venus, where runaway greenhouse effect
失控的溫室效應把它變成一座煉獄
has turned it into a kind of hell.
火星
Mars...
表面積和地球相近
a world with as much land as Earth itself.
一條岩石似的小行星帶
A belt of rocky asteroids circles the Sun
在火星和木星的軌道間圍繞太陽運行
between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter.
木星被四個大衛星和幾十個小衛星環繞
With its four giant moons and dozens of smaller ones,
木星好像擁有自己的太陽系一般
Jupiter is like its own little solar system.
它的質量超過所有其他行星的總和
It has more mass than all the other planets combined.
木星的大紅斑
Jupiter's Great Red Spot...
它是一個比地球大3倍的古老風暴
a hurricane three times the size of our whole planet
已經存在了幾百年之久
that's been raging for centuries.
土星宛如太陽系中皇冠上的明珠
The crown jewel of our solar system, Saturn,
被無數運行軌道和緩慢翻滾的雪球所環繞
ringed by freeways of countless orbiting and slowly tumbling snowballs...
每個雪球的體積相當於一個小月亮
every snowball, a little moon.
天王星
Uranus...
還有海王星
and Neptune,
這顆古人未知的最偏遠的行星
the outermost planets, unknown to the ancients
直到望遠鏡發明後才被發現
and only discovered after the invention of the telescope.
在這最偏遠的行星之外
Beyond the outermost planet,
還有成千上萬的冰凍世界
there's a swarm of tens of thousands of frozen worlds.
冥王星就是其中一個
And Pluto is one them.
在我們所有的航天器中
Of all our spacecraft,
這是離家最遠的一個
this is the one that's traveled farthest from home...
旅行者1號
Voyager 1.
於1977年9月5日發射 截止到2012年6月仍然正常運作
它是有史以來距離地球最遠的人造飛行器
她承載著我們發向未來的信息
She bears a message to a billion years from now,
歷經36年的旅行 離地球約187億公里 是第一個離開太陽系的人造飛行器
關於我們是誰
something of who we were,
旅行者1號上攜帶了一張銅質磁盤唱片 內容包括用55種人類語言錄製的問候語和各類音樂
旨在向「外星人」表達人類的問候
我們的體會
how we felt
55種人類語言中包括了四種中國的語言:粵語 國語 閩南語 吳語
問候語為：「行星地球的孩子（向你們）問好」
以及我們創作的音樂
and the music we made.
浩瀚宇宙海洋中
The deeper waters
更深層的水流裏
of this vast cosmic ocean
也存在著數不盡的世界
and their numberless worlds lie ahead.
從這裏看 太陽好像和其他星星並無兩樣
From out here, the Sun may look like just another star.
但它的引力場依然影響著
But it still exerts its gravitational hold
數萬億的冰凍彗星
on a trillion frozen comets,
還有太陽系中那些形成於大約50億年前的
leftovers from the formation of the solar system
其他所有組成部分
nearly five billion years ago.
我們稱之為 奧爾特雲
It's called the Oort Cloud.
以前從沒有人見過 也不可能見過
No one has ever seen it before, nor could they,
因為這些天體
because each one of these little worlds
與它最近的鄰居之間的距離
is as far from its nearest neighbor
和地球與土星的距離差不多 (12-16億公里）
as Earth is from Saturn.
這個包含太陽系的巨大彗星雲團
This enormous cloud of comets encloses the solar system,
就是我們宇宙地址的第二行
which is the second line of our cosmic address.
地球
太陽系
我們有能力探測其他星系的行星
We've only been able to detect the planets of other stars
也就是最近幾十年的事情
for a few decades,
但是我們已經知道行星的數量是很多的
but we already know that planets are plentiful...
比恆星的數量要多得多
they outnumber the stars.
幾乎所有的行星都和地球很不一樣
Almost all of them will be very different from Earth,
不適合生物生存
and hostile to life as we know it.
但是我們對於生物又有多少瞭解呢？
But what do we know about life?
目前我們只接觸過一種
We've met only one kind so far.
地球生物
Earthlife.
看到什麼了嗎？
See anything?
只是空蕩蕩的太空 對嗎
Just empty space, right?
人類的眼睛只能看到宇宙中的一絲光亮
Human eyes see only a sliver of the light that shines in the cosmos.
但是科技讓我們可以看到肉眼無法看到的
But science gives us the power to see what our senses cannot.
夜視鏡可以讓我們看見紅外線
Infrared is the kind of light made visible by night-vision goggles.
向黑暗中發射一個紅外感應器
Throw an infrared sensor across the darkness...
流浪行星
Rogue planet.
不繞恆星公轉的行星
World without a sun.
我們的銀河中有數十億顆遊蕩在永恆的黑夜中
Our galaxy has billions of them, adrift in perpetual night.
在他們原本的星系誕生時的混亂中
They're orphans, cast away from their mother stars
他們像孤兒一樣失去了恆星母親
during the chaotic birth of their native star systems.
流浪行星有著熔岩般的內核
Rogue planets are molten at the core
但表面卻被嚴寒覆蓋
but frozen at the surface.
在這些極端區域的中間
There may be oceans of liquid water
也許存在著大洋般的液態水
in the zone between those extremes.
誰又能知道水中生活著什麼東西呢
Who knows what might be swimming there?
這是銀河的紅外線顯示圖
This is what the Milky Way looks like in infrared.
每個小點 不僅僅是那些明亮的
Every single dot, not just the bright ones,
都是一顆恆星
is a star.
這裏有多少顆恆星
How many stars?
有多少不同的世界呢
How many worlds?
又有多少不同的生命存在的方式
How many ways of being alive?
我們又身處圖片中的何處呢
Where are we in this picture?
地球
太陽系
銀河系
看到那條螺旋臂了嗎
See that trailing outer arm?
我們就在那裏
That's where we live...
距離中心3萬光年
about 30,000 light-years from the center.
銀河系
The Milky Way Galaxy
我們宇宙地址的下一行
is the next line of our cosmic address.
我們現在離家十萬光年
We're now a hundred thousand light-years from home.
光波 存在的速度最快的東西
It would take light, the fastest thing there is,
要花10萬年才能從地球到達我們這裏
a hundred thousand years to reach us from Earth.
這是僊女座螺旋星系
This is the Great Spiral in Andromeda,
銀河系的隔壁鄰居
the galaxy next door.
我們將這兩大星系
We call our two giant galaxies
和一些較小的星系稱為
and a smattering of smaller ones
本星系群
the "local group."
地球
太陽系
銀河系
本星系群
從這裏已經看不到銀河系了
Can't even find our home galaxy from out here.
它只是室女座超星系團中的幾千份之一
It's just one of thousands in the Virgo Supercluster.
地球
太陽系
銀河系
本星系群
室女座超星系團
以這個比例來說
On this scale,
我們所看到的 哪怕是最小的點
all the objects we see, including the tiniest dots,
都是一個星系
are galaxies.
每個星系包含幾十億顆恆星
Each galaxy contains billions of suns
和數不清的行星世界
and countless worlds.
然而 整個室女座超星系團
Yet, the entire Virgo Supercluster itself
只是我們宇宙的一個極小組成部分
forms but a tiny part of our universe.
這是我們已知的最大範圍的宇宙
This is the cosmos on the grandest scale we know...
一張由數以千億的星系組成的大網
a network of a hundred billion galaxies.
也是我們宇宙地址的最後一行
It's the last line of our cosmic address...
地球
太陽系
銀河系
本星系群 室女座超星系團
可觀測宇宙
截止目前
for now.
可觀測宇宙
Observable universe?!
什麼意思
What does that mean?
即使我們在想像之舟中
Even for us, in our Ship of the Imagination,
在時空中所能看到的也是有限的
there's a limit to how far we can see in space-time.
這是我們的宇宙水平線
It's our cosmic horizon.
一部分的宇宙處於水平線之下
Beyond that horizon lie parts of the universe
離我們實在太遙遠了
that are too far away.
在僅有的時間裏
There hasn't been enough time
在宇宙138億年的歷史中
in the 13.8 billion year history of the universe
光線還來不及傳遞過來
for their light to have reached us.
很多人猜測 所有的這一切
Many of us suspect that all of this...
所有的行星 恆星 星系 星團
all the worlds, stars, galaxies and clusters
我們的可觀測宇宙中的一切
in our observable universe...
只是其他宇宙中的滄海一粟
is but one tiny bubble in an infinite ocean of other universes...
多重宇宙論
...a multiverse.
宇宙之上的宇宙
Universe upon universe.
沒有盡頭的世界
Worlds without end.
感覺很渺小嗎
Feeling a little small?
相對宇宙來說 我們確實很渺小
Well, in the contexts of the cosmos, we are small.
我們或許只是生活在這浩瀚宇宙中
We may just be little guys living on a speck of dust,
漂浮的灰塵粒上的小不點
afloat in a staggering immensity,
但我們並不坐井觀天
but we don't think small.
現在的宇宙論誕生並不久遠
This cosmic perspective is relatively new.
僅僅400年前 我們尚未認識
A mere four centuries ago, our tiny world was oblivious
自身世界以外的宇宙
to the rest of the cosmos.
那時沒有望遠鏡
There were no telescopes.
只能看到我們肉眼可見的部分
The universe was only what you could see with the naked eye.
在1599年
Back in 1599,
所有人都認為太陽 行球 星星
everyone knew that the Sun, planets and stars
只是環繞地球的亮光
were just lights in the sky that revolved around the Earth,
而我們是宇宙的中心
and that we were the center of a little universe,
由上帝為我們創造的宇宙
a universe made for us.
當時全世界只有一個人
There was only one man on the whole planet
想像著一個無盡的浩瀚宇宙
who envisioned an infinitely grander cosmos.
他是怎麼度過他的1600年除夕？
And how was he spending New Year's Eve of the year 1600?
當然是在監獄裏
Why, in prison, of course.
生命中總有那麼一天
There comes a time in our lives
我們發現自己並不是宇宙的中心
when we first realize we're not the center of the universe,
我們以外還有更廣大的世界
that we belong to something much greater than ourselves.
這是我們成長所需經歷的一部分
It's part of growing up.
因為每個人都會經歷到這段過程
And as it happens to each of us,
我們的文明也在16世紀
so it began to happen to our civilization
也經歷著這樣的成長
in the 16th century.
想像一下望遠鏡問世之前
Imagine a world before telescopes,
我們只能靠肉眼觀察這個宇宙
when the universe was only what you could see with the naked eye.
很顯然地球是靜止不動的
It was obvious that Earth was motionless,
天空中的一切
and that everything in the heavens...
太陽 月亮 星星 星球
the Sun, the Moon, the stars, the planets...
都圍繞著我們運行  然後
revolved around us... and then...
一位名叫哥白尼的波蘭天文學家兼牧師
a Polish astronomer and priest named Copernicus
提出一個地球並非中心的激進假想
made a radical proposal. The Earth was not the center.
地球只是和其他星星一樣的行星繞著太陽旋轉
It was just one of the planets, and, like them, it revolved around the Sun.
很多人 例如宗教改革發起人馬丁·路德
Many, like the Protestant reformer Martin Luther,
認為這是在對聖經的可恥侮辱
took this idea as a scandalous affront to Scripture.
他們震怒了
They were horrified.
但是另一個人卻認為哥白尼說的不全面
But for one man, Copernicus didn't go far enough.
他叫焦爾達諾·布魯諾
His name was Giordano Bruno and he was a natural-born rebel.
他生性反叛
and he was a natural-born rebel.
他渴望打破這狹隘宇宙的枷鎖
He longed to bust out of that cramped little universe.
在那不勒斯做道明會的修道士時
Even as a young Dominican monk in Naples,
他就與這個世界格格不入
he was a misfit.
當時在意大利沒有思想的自由
This was a time when there was no freedom of thought in Italy.
但是布魯諾渴望瞭解
But Bruno hungered to know
關於上帝創世的一切
everything about God's creation.
他閱讀了被教廷禁止的書籍
He dared to read the books banned by the Church,
從此踏上了不歸路
and that was his undoing.
這些書籍中
In one of them,
有一本的作者是1500年前的古羅馬人
an ancient Roman, a man dead for more than 1,500 years
物性論 - 盧克·萊修
向他描述了一個更廣闊的宇宙
whispered to him of a universe far greater,
廣闊的猶如他的上帝一般
one as boundless as his idea of God.
盧克萊修讓他的讀者
Lucretius asked the reader
想像站在宇宙的邊緣
to imagine standing at the edge of the universe
向外射出一支箭
and shooting an arrow outward.
如果箭繼續前進 那麼很明顯
If the arrow keeps going, then clearly,
宇宙繼續向所謂的邊緣以外延伸
the universe extends beyond what you thought was the edge.
但是如果箭不繼續前進
But if the arrow doesn't keep going...
比方說 撞在一堵牆上
say it hits a wall... then that wall must lie
那麼牆必然是處在所謂的邊緣之外
beyond what you thought was the edge of the universe.
那麼如果你站在這堵牆上向外射箭
Now if you stand on that wall and shoot another arrow,
也只有這相同的兩個結果
there are only the same two possible outcomes...
要麼是飛入無盡的太空
it either flies forever out into space,
要麼是撞在某個障礙物上
or it hits some boundary
然後你又可以站在上面射出另一支箭
where you can stand and shoot yet another arrow.
無論如何 宇宙是沒有界限的
Either way, the universe is unbounded.
宇宙必然是無盡的
The cosmos must be infinite.
布魯諾深以為然
This made perfect sense to Bruno.
他崇拜的上帝是全能的
The God he worshiped was infinite.
所以他斷定 上帝創造的宇宙怎會不是無窮
So how, he reasoned, could Creation be anything less?
那是他的最後一份穩定工作
It was the last steady job he ever had.
後來 當他30歲時
And then, when he was 30,
他的一個幻覺從此改變他的一生
he had the vision that sealed his fate.
在這個夢中 他認識到了
In this dream, he awakened to a world
一個包含在一群行星中的世界
enclosed inside a confining bowl of stars.
就是他那個時代的宇宙
This was the cosmos of Bruno's time.
他感到一陣不舒服的害怕
He experienced a sickening moment of fear,
就像腳下的一切
as if the bottom of everything
正向下墜落
was falling away beneath his feet.
但是他鼓起了勇氣
But he summoned up his courage.
我展開自信的翅膀飛向太空
I spread confident wings to space
向上高飛至無盡的天空
and soared toward the infinite, leaving far behind me
將一切的壓力拋在身後
what others strained to see from a distance.
這裏沒有上 沒有下 沒有邊界
Here, there was no up, no down, no edge,
沒有中心
no center.
我看見太陽和其他星星一樣
I saw that the Sun was just another star,
還有其他被行星伴隨著的恆星
and the stars were other Suns, each escorted by other Earths
就像我們的太陽
like our own.
這巨大的啟示對他就如同墜入愛河
The revelation of this immensity was like falling in love.
布魯諾變成了一個傳教士
Bruno became an evangelist,
他在歐洲各地宣揚他的宇宙無限論
spreading the gospel of infinity throughout Europe.
他以為其他上帝的追隨者會同樣接受
He assumed that other lovers of God would naturally embrace
這個對於創世的偉大且榮耀的觀點
this grander and more glorious view of Creation.
我是不是太傻了
What a fool I was.
在他的祖國 他被羅馬天主教會開除教籍
He was excommunicated by the Roman Catholic Church in his homeland,
他不僅被瑞士加爾文長老會驅逐出境
expelled by the Calvinists in Switzerland,
還被德國的路德教派驅逐出境
and by the Lutherans in Germany.
布魯諾接受了一份邀請到英國牛津大學講課
Bruno jumped at an invitation to lecture at Oxford, in England.
他認為這是一個機會
At last, he thought,
可以與他類似的人分享他的觀點
a chance to share his vision with an audience of his peers.
我來介紹一個對於宇宙的嶄新看法
I have come to present a new vision of the cosmos.
哥白尼是對的
Copernicus was right to argue that our world
我們的世界並不是宇宙的中心
is not the center of the universe.
地球繞著太陽旋轉
The Earth goes around the Sun.
它和其他行星一樣
It's a planet, just like the others.
但哥白尼只是曙光
But Copernicus was only the dawn.
而我為你們帶來日出
I bring you the sunrise.
那些星星和我們炙熱的太陽一樣
The stars are other fiery suns,
由和地球一樣的天體組成
made of the same substance as the Earth,
他們也有自己的含水的地球
and they have their own watery earths,
上面有著和我們一樣高貴的動物植物
with plants and animals no less noble than our own.
你是瘋了還是太蠢
Are you mad or merely ignorant?
眾所周知只有一個世界
Everyone knows there is only one world.
那是錯誤的
What everyone knows is wrong.
我們全能的上帝創造了一個無邊無際的宇宙
Our infinite God has created a boundless universe
其中包含了無數的星球
with an infinite number of worlds.
你們那的人沒讀過亞里斯多德的書嗎
Do they not read Aristotle where you come from?
或者是聖經嗎
Or even the Bible?
我請求你摒棄老舊和傳統的信仰和權威
I beg you, reject antiquity, tradition, faith, and authority.
讓我們重新認識
Let us begin anew,
質疑我們以為
by doubting everything we assume
-已經被證實的一切 -異端者!
- has been proven. - Heretic!
異教徒
Infidel!
你們信仰的上帝太小了
Your God is too small.
明智的人本應該從中吸取了教訓
A wiser man would have learned his lesson.
可惜布魯諾並不是那個人
But Bruno was not such a man.
他不停的宣揚自己觀點
He couldn't keep his soaring vision of the cosmos to himself,
儘管這會帶來沉痛的代價
despite the fact that the penalty for doing so
在他的那個時代 代價是如此的殘酷
in his world was the most vicious form
無情和更嚴厲的懲罰
of cruel and unusual punishment.
焦爾達諾·布魯諾生活的那個時代
Giordano Bruno lived at a time when there was no such thing
沒有政教分離
as the separation of church and state,
沒有言論自由神聖不可侵犯
or the notion that freedom of speech was a sacred right of every individual.
表達與傳統信仰相悖的觀點
Expressing an idea that didn't conform to traditional belief
會帶來極大的麻煩
could land you in deep trouble.
布魯諾不顧一切地回到了意大利
Recklessly, Bruno returned to Italy.
也許是想家了
Maybe he was homesick.
可是他必須知道
But still, he must have known that his homeland
他的祖國對他來說
was one of the most dangerous places in Europe
是最危險的國家
he could possibly go.
由羅馬天主教會管轄的宗教法庭
The Roman Catholic Church maintained a system of courts
被稱為異端裁判所
known as the Inquisition,
它唯一職責就是審查和折磨
and its sole purpose was to investigate and torment
與教會持有不同聲音和觀點的人
anyone who dared voice views that differed from theirs.
布魯諾很快就被
It wasn't long before Bruno fell into the clutches
思想警察抓獲
of the thought police.
這位信奉無限宇宙的流浪者
This wanderer, who worshiped an infinite universe,
在八年的監獄生涯中飽受煎熬
languished in confinement for eight years.
儘管受盡殘酷的審訊
Through relentless interrogations,
他依然不願放棄他的觀點
he stubbornly refused to renounce his views.
為什麼教會要花
Why was the Church willing
如此長的時間來折磨布魯諾
to go to such lengths to torment Bruno?
他們在害怕什麼
What were they afraid of?
如果布魯諾是對的 那麼這些聖典
If Bruno was right, then the sacred books
還有教會的權威
and the authority of the Church
都將會受到質疑
would be open to question.
最終 異端裁判所的紅衣主教們
Finally, the cardinals of the Inquisition
做出了他們的判決
rendered their verdict.
你有罪
You are found guilty
你質疑聖父聖子聖靈三位一體
of questioning the Holy Trinity
你質疑耶穌基督的神威
and the divinity of Jesus Christ.
你相信上帝的怒火不會永遠
Of believing that God's wrath is not eternal,
所有人都會被寬恕
that everyone will be saved.
你斷言其他世界存在的主張
Of asserting the existence of other worlds.
你寫的所有書
All of the books you have written
都會在聖彼得廣場前焚燬
will be gathered up and burned in St. Peter's Square.
尊敬的大人 8年的監禁
Reverend Father, these eight years of confinement
給了我很多時間去反省
have given me much time to reflect.
然後呢
So...
你要放棄你的主張嗎
you will recant?
我對造物主的愛和崇敬
My love and reverence for the Creator
激發我對全能的上帝的認識
inspires in me the vision of an infinite Creation.
如果你拒不懺悔的話
You shall be turned over to the Governor of Rome
你會被移交到羅馬總督
to administer the appropriate punishment
予以執行相應的懲罰
for those who will not repent.
可能你宣佈這個判決時的恐懼
It may be that you are more afraid
比我聽到判決的時候更厲害
to deliver this judgment than I am to hear it.
布魯諾殉難的10年後
Ten years after Bruno's martyrdom,
伽利略通過望遠鏡
Galileo first looked through a telescope,
發現布魯諾的學說確實沒錯
realizing that Bruno had been right all along.
銀河系是由肉眼看不到的無數恆星組成
The Milky Way was made of countless stars invisible to the naked eye,
天空中的某些光亮其實是其他的行星
and some of those lights in the sky were actually other worlds.
布魯諾不是科學家
Bruno was no scientist.
他只是僥倖猜中了
His vision of the cosmos was a lucky guess,
因為沒有證據支持他
because he had no evidence to support it.
就和其他猜想一樣 也有可能不對
Like most guesses, it could well have turned out wrong.
但是這個觀點一旦散播出去
But once the idea was in the air,
它就給了其他人一個方向
it gave others a target to aim at.
哪怕只是為了反駁
If only to disprove it.
布魯諾大致理解了太空的浩瀚無垠
Bruno glimpsed the vastness of space.
但他對於時間的驚人無際沒有絲毫概念
But he had no inkling of the staggering immensity of time.
壽命很少超過一個世紀的普通人
How can we humans, who rarely live more than a century,
怎麼可能去理解宇宙的歷史
hope to grasp the vast expanse of time
就像浩瀚寬闊的時間長河
that is the history of the cosmos?
宇宙誕生於138億年前
The universe is 13.8 thousand million years old.
為了更好地想像宇宙的歷史
In order to imagine all of cosmic time,
我們把它壓縮成12個月的年歷
let's compress it into a single calendar year.
年歷上的1月1號是宇宙誕生的日子
The cosmic calendar begins on January 1st with the birth of our universe.
年歷上包含了從那以後經歷的所有時間
It contains everything that's happened since then,
一直到現在
up to now,
在這個年歷上的12月31號午夜
which on this calendar is midnight December 31st.
按照這個比例 每個月代表10億年
On this scale, every month represents about a billion years.
每天代表將就4千萬年
Every day represents nearly 40 million years.
讓我們盡可能地回到過去
Let's go back as far as we can,
回到宇宙最開始的時刻
to the very first moment of the universe.
1月1號 宇宙大爆炸
January 1st, the Big Bang.
目前而言這是我們所能看到最早的時間
It's as far back as we can see in time... for now.
整個宇宙形成於一個比原子還小的點
Our entire universe emerged from a point smaller than a single atom.
空間在密度極大溫度極高的狀態下爆炸
Space itself exploded in a cosmic fire,
由此開始了宇宙的擴張
launching the expansion of the universe
並誕生了所有的能量
and giving birth to all the energy
還有已經產生的那些所有我們已知的事物
and all the matter we know today.
聽上去很瘋狂
I know that sounds crazy,
但是我們有很強力的觀測證據
but there's strong observational evidence
來支持宇宙大爆炸理論
to support the Big Bang theory.
證據還有氦元素在宇宙中的比例
And it includes the amount of helium in the cosmos
以及爆炸殘留的發光無線電頻譜
and the glow of radio waves left over from the explosion.
爆炸後宇宙開始冷卻
As it expanded, the universe cooled,
其間有2億年左右的黑暗
and there was darkness for about 200 million years.
萬有引力將氣體集聚並且加熱
Gravity was pulling together clumps of gas and heating them
直到第一批恆星發出亮光
until the first stars burst into light
相當於1月10號
on January 10th.
1月13號 這些恆星開始結合
On January 13th, these stars coalesced
形成第一批小星系
into the first small galaxies.
這些星系融合成更大的星系
These galaxies merged to form still larger ones,
包括我們的銀河系
including our own Milky Way,
產生於110億年左右
which formed about 11 billion years ago,
就是宇宙年歷上的3月15號
on March 15th of the cosmic year.
數千億的恆星中
Hundreds of billions of suns.
哪個是我們的太陽
Which one is ours?
此時尚未誕生
It's not yet born.
它將從其他恆星的灰燼中產生
It will rise from the ashes of other stars.
看到這些猶如閃光燈般的亮光嗎
See those lights flashing like paparazzi?
它們都是超新星
Each one is a supernova,
一顆超大恆星的耀眼爆炸
the blazing death of a giant star.
恆星消亡和誕生的地方
Stars die and are born in places like this one...
我們稱為星星苗圃
a stellar nursery.
又稱分子雲
他們像雨滴般
They condense like raindrops
從巨大的氣態和灰塵雲中凝結
from giant clouds of gas and dust.
他們溫度高的可以把原子中的原子核
They get so hot that the nuclei of the atoms
融合在一起
fuse together deep within them
從而產生了我們呼吸的氧氣 肌肉中的碳元素
to make the oxygen we breathe, the carbon in our muscles,
骨頭中的鈣元素 血中的鐵元素
the calcium in our bones, the iron in our blood,
所有的這一切都產生於
all of it was cooked
從此消亡的恆星炙熱的內心
in the fiery hearts of long-vanished stars.
你 我 所有人
You, me, everyone...
我們都是由星辰物質組成
we are made of star stuff.
星辰物質被不斷循環和濃縮
This star stuff is recycled and enriched,
一遍又一遍
again and again,
經過幾代恆星的誕生消亡
through succeeding generations of stars.
離我們的太陽誕生還有多久
How much longer until the birth of our Sun?
很長時間
A long time.
我們太陽的第一次發光
It won't begin to shine
還要再等60億年
for another six billion years.
太陽的生日是8月31號
Our Sun's birthday is August 31st
在這個宇宙年歷上
on the Cosmic Calendar...
45億年前
...four and a half billion years ago.
就像太陽系中其他行星
As with the other worlds of our solar system,
地球在一堆氣體和灰塵中產生
Earth was formed from a disk of gas and dust
繞著新生的太陽運行
orbiting the newborn Sun.
反覆的碰撞產生了一個發光的球狀碎片
Repeated collisions produced a growing ball of debris.
看到那個小行星了嗎
See that asteroid?
不是那個
No, not that one.
那邊的那個
The one over there.
我們的存在歸功於它旁邊的引力
We exist because the gravity of that one next to it
把它輕輕向左推了一英吋
just nudged it an inch to the left.
一英吋有很大的區別嗎
What difference could an inch make
按照太陽系的比例來說
on the scale the solar system?
稍等 你馬上就能看到
Just wait, you'll see.
在最初的10億年裏
The Earth took one hell of a beating
地球飽受摧殘
in its first billion years.
任由軌道上的碎片撞擊和融合
Fragments of orbiting debris collided and coalesced,
直到他們形成了我們的月亮
until they snowballed to form our Moon.
月亮是那個暴力紀元的紀念品
The Moon is a souvenir of that violent epoch.
如果你站在遠古地球的表面
If you stood on the surface of that long ago Earth,
月亮會看上去比現在亮100倍
the Moon would have looked a hundred times brighter.
那時月亮離我們近10倍
It was ten times closer back then,
被比現在更強大的引力場吸引著
locked in a much more intimate gravitational embrace.
地球冷卻下來 海洋形成了
As the Earth cooled, seas began to form.
海浪比現在高1000倍
The tides were a thousand times higher then.
經過極漫長的時間 潮汐的摩擦力
Over the eons, tidal friction within Earth
將月球推遠
pushed the Moon away.
生命差不多在這個時候誕生
Life began somewhere around here,
9月21號
September 21st,
在地球上的35億年前
three and a half billion years ago on our little world.
我們依然不知道生命如何起源
We still don't know how life got started.
我們只是知道
For all we know,
有可能是來自銀河系的其他地方
it may have come from another part of the Milky Way.
生命的起源
The origin of life
是最偉大的未知科學奇跡之一
is one of the greatest unsolved mysteries of science.
生命的演變
That's life cooking,
一切生物化學的進化
evolving all the biochemical recipes
充滿了無與倫比的複雜活動
for its incredibly complex activities.
到了11月9號 生命開始呼吸 移動
By November 9th, life was breathing, moving,
進食和對週遭環境作出反應
eating, responding to its environment.
多虧了這些有開拓性的微生物
We owe a lot to those pioneering microbes.
沒錯 就是這些不起眼的傢伙
Oh, yeah... one other thing.
他們還發明了繁殖
They also invented sex.
12月17號 很特別的一天
December 17th was quite a day.
海洋中生命的發展開始騰飛
Life in the sea really took off,
形形色色的大型植物和動物
it was exploding with a diversity
爆炸式地發展
of larger plants and animals.
提塔利克魚是最早冒險登陸的動物之一
Tiktaalik was one of the first animals to venture onto land.
感覺肯定像是造訪另一個星球
It must have felt like visiting another planet.
森林  恐龍
Forests, dinosaurs,
鳥類 昆蟲
birds, insects,
都在12月的最後一周進化而來
they all evolved in the final week of December.
第一朵花
The first flower...
在12月28號 盛開
bloomed on December 28th.
隨著古森林的成長死亡
As these ancient forests grew and died
並被深埋進地下
and sank beneath the surface,
他們的殘骸形成了煤
their remains transformed into coal.
3億年後
300 million years later,
人類燃燒這些煤來推動文明的發展
we humans are burning most of that coal to power
同時也使我們的文明陷入危機
and imperil our civilization.
還記得那顆在太陽系形成時的
Remember that asteroid back in the formation
小行星嗎
of the solar system...
那顆被輕輕推動的小行星
the one that got nudged a little to the left?
它來了
Well, here it comes.
宇宙年歷上的12月30號 早晨6點24分
It's 6:24 AM on December 30th on the Cosmic Calendar.
在1億年的時間裏
For more than a hundred million years,
恐龍曾是這個地球的統治者
the dinosaurs were lords of the Earth,
當我們的祖先 小型哺乳動物
while our ancestors, small mammals,
戰戰兢兢地在地面爬來爬去的時候
scurried fearfully underfoot.
這顆小行星改變了一切
The asteroid changed all that.
假如它沒有被推動
Suppose it hadn't been nudged at all.
它會完全和地球擦肩而過
It would have missed the Earth entirely,
恐龍恐怕依然存在
and for all we know, the dinosaurs might still be here
但我們不會
but we wouldn't.
這是極端突發狀況的好例子
This is a good example of the extreme contingency,
生存的偶然性
the chance nature, of existence.
宇宙已經誕生超過135億年
The universe is already more than 13 and a half billion years old.
人類仍未出現
Still no sign of us.
在這個年歷代表的時間長河中
In the vast ocean of time that this calendar represents,
人類在宇宙年歷中的最後一天
we humans only evolved within the last hour
最後一小時進化而來
of the last day of the cosmic year.
11點59分46秒
11:59 and 46 seconds.
全部有記載的歷史發生在最後的14秒裏
All of recorded history occupies only the last 14 seconds,
你聽說過的所有人
and every person you've ever heard of
存在於這個點的某個位置
lived somewhere in there.
那些國王 戰役 遷徙 發明
All those kings and battles, migrations and inventions,
戰爭和愛情 寫在歷史書中的一切
wars and loves, everything in the history books
都發生在這宇宙年歷中的最後幾秒
happened here, in the last seconds of the Cosmic Calendar.
但如果我們想要研究
But if we want to explore
宇宙年歷中這段極短的時間
such a brief moment of cosmic time...
我們必須改變比例
...we'll have to change scale.
我們是這個宇宙的新丁
We are newcomers to the cosmos.
我們的歷史僅僅從宇宙年的最後一晚開始
Our own story only begins on the last night of the cosmic year.
現在是新年前夜的9點45分
It's 9:45 on New Year's Eve.
350萬年前
Three and a half million years ago,
你我的祖先留下這些足跡
our ancestors, yours and mine, left these traces.
我們站了起來和他們區別開來
We stood up, and parted ways from them.
自從我們直立行走
Once we were standing on two feet,
我們的雙眼不在迷戀地面
our eyes were no longer fixated on the ground.
現在我們可以自由的探索奇跡
Now we were free to look up in wonder.
人類存在的大部分時間裏
For the longest part of human existence,
比方說最近的4萬代人
say the last 40,000 generations,
我們曾是流浪者
we were wanderers,
獵人和採集者混住在一起
living in small bands of hunters and gatherers,
製作工具 生火
making tools, controlling fire,
給事物起名字
naming things,
都發生在宇宙年歷的最後一個小時裏
all within the last hour of the Cosmic Calendar.
我們必須改變比例去繼續探尋
To find out what happens next, we'll have to change scale
最後一晚的最後一分鐘
to see the last minute of the last night
發生了什麼
of the cosmic year.
11點59分
11:59
以宇宙時間比例來說我們太太太年輕了
We're so very young on the time scale of the universe
我們甚至還沒開始畫出第一張畫
that we didn't start painting our first pictures
直到宇宙年歷的最後60秒
until the last 60 seconds of the cosmic year,
只不過是3萬年前
a mere 30,000 years ago.
我們發明了天文學
This is when we invented astronomy.
事實上我們都是天文學家的後裔
In fact, we're all descended from astronomers.
我們的生存要依靠研究星星
Our survival depended on knowing how to read the stars
用來預測冬天的到來
in order to predict the coming of the winter
以及獸群的遷徙
and the migration of the wild herds.
然後大約1萬年前
And then, around 10,000 years ago,
我們的生活方式迎來了變革
there began a revolution in the way we lived.
我們的祖先學會了如何改變周圍環境
Our ancestors learned how to shape their environment,
栽培植物 馴養動物
taming wild plants and animals,
耕作土地 定居下來
cultivating land and settling down.
這改變了一切
This changed everything.
有史以來第一次
For the first time in our history,
我們可以擁有超過我們負重能力的東西
we had more stuff than we could carry.
我們需要把這些數量記錄下來
We needed a way to keep track of it.
午夜前的14秒
At 14 seconds to midnight,
大約6千年前 我們發明了書寫
or about 6,000 years ago, we invented writing.
隨後不久我們就開始記錄其他東西
And it wasn't long before we started recording
不僅僅是糧食的數量
more than bushels of grain.
書寫讓我們保存我們的想法
Writing allowed us to save our thoughts
並且跨越時間和空間的傳播它們
and send them much further in space and time.
泥板上的細小印記
Tiny markings on a clay tablet
成了我們征服有限的生命的手段
became a means for us to vanquish mortality.
震撼了整個世界
It shook the world.
摩西出生於7秒之前
Moses was born seven seconds ago.
釋迦摩尼 6秒前
Buddha, six seconds ago.
耶穌基督 5秒前
Jesus, five seconds ago.
穆罕穆德 3秒前
Mohammed, three seconds ago.
不到2秒前 不論好壞
It was not even two seconds ago that, for better or worse,
地球一邊的人類發現了地球的另一邊
the two halves of the Earth discovered each other.
僅僅在最後的一秒鐘里
And it was only in the very last second
我們開始使用科學
of the Cosmic Calendar that we began to use science
去揭示大自然的秘密和規則
to reveal nature's secrets and her laws.
科學方法是如此的強大
The scientific method is so powerful
只用了4個世紀的時間
that in a mere four centuries,
就從伽利略第一次看向望遠鏡
it has taken us from Galileo's first look through a telescope
到人類在月球上留下足跡
at another world to leaving our footprints on the Moon.
它讓我們可以越過時間和空間
It allowed us to look out across space and time
去觀察我們在宇宙時空中的位置
to discover where and when we are in the cosmos.
我們有了瞭解宇宙本質的辦法
We are a way for the cosmos to know itself.
卡爾·薩根30多年前帶領我們進行了首次的宇宙航行
Carl Sagan guided the maiden voyage of Cosmos a generation ago.
他不僅是20世紀最成功的
He was the most successful science communicator
科學傳播者
of the 20th century,
也是一位首屈一指的科學家
but he was first and foremost a scientist.
卡爾為我們瞭解行星
Carl contributed enormously
作出了極大的貢獻
to our knowledge of the planets.
他正確地預測了木星的衛星 泰坦 土衛六上
He correctly predicted the existence of methane lakes
有沼氣湖的存在
on Saturn's giant moon Titan.
他指出早期地球的大氣層中
He showed that the atmosphere of the early Earth
必然含有強大的溫室氣體
must have contained powerful greenhouse gases.
他首先推斷出火星上的季節變化
He was the first to understand that seasonal changes on Mars
是由沙塵暴引起
were due to windblown dust.
卡爾是一位
Carl was a pioneer
在探索地球以外智慧生物領域的先驅
in the search for extraterrestrial life and intelligence.
太空時代的最初40年裏 每次主要的
He played a leading role in every major spacecraft mission
太陽系探索航天任務 他都擔任了重要的職務
to explore the solar system during the first 40 years of the Space Age.
但他做的 不僅僅只有這些
But that's not all he did.
這是卡爾的一本1975年的記事日曆
This is Carl Sagan's own calendar from 1975.
我那時在做什麼
Who was I back then?
12月20日 奈爾·德葛拉司·泰森
我只是一個紐約的17歲男孩
I was just a 17-year-old kid from the Bronx
夢想著可以成為科學家
with dreams of becoming a scientist,
世界上最著名的天文學家
and somehow the world's most famous astronomer found time
邀請我去紐約州
to invite me to Ithaca, in upstate New York,
和他共度一個週六
and spend a Saturday with him.
我記得那天下著雪
I remember that snowy day like it was yesterday.
他來公車站接我
He met me at the bus stop
帶我參觀了他在康奈爾大學的實驗室
and showed me his laboratory at Cornell University.
卡爾從書桌後拿出這本書並在上面為我題字
Carl reached behind his desk and inscribed this book for me.
《宇宙的聯繫》(The Cosmic Connection)
"致 尼爾 未來的天文學家
"For Neil, a future astronomer.
卡爾"
Carl."
結束後 他開車送我去公車站
At the end of the day, he drove me back to the bus station.
雪下得更大了
The snow was falling harder.
他寫下他的電話號碼 家裏的電話
He wrote his phone number... his home phone number...
寫在一張小紙片上 然後跟我說 "如果公車沒有來
on a scrap of paper and he said, "If the bus can't get through,
打電話給我 就在我家過夜"
call me and spend the night at my home with my family."
我當時已經決定要當一名科學家
I already knew I wanted to become a scientist,
但是那天下午 我認識到
but that afternoon, I learned from Carl
我要做他那樣的人
the kind of person I wanted to become.
他幫助了我 還有其他很多人
He reached out to me and to countless others,
激勵我們去學習 教授 研究科學
inspiring so many of us to study, teach and do science.
科學研究是一份需要合作的事業
Science is a cooperative enterprise,
持續幾代人的時間
spanning the generations.
就如同一支火炬在老師與學生的手中傳遞
It's the passing of a torch from teacher to student to teacher,
一群偉大的思想從遠古貫穿
a community of minds reaching back to antiquity
直至未來的星空
and forward to the stars.
現在跟我來
Now, come with me.
我們的旅程才剛剛開始
Our journey is just beginning.
中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain timhal
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息